Today's daf is בבא קמא קט"ז, Bava Kamma Kuf-Tes-Zayin, בבא קמא Bava
Kamma 116, we're a little behind we pick up on קט"ו עמוד
ב' Kuf-Tes-Vav Amud Bet 115B, about 25 lines down, almost exactly in
the middle. Line starts with the word עליה aleha and we're one
word in, בשלמא. bishlema. And our learning should be in the עילוי
נשמת ilui nishmat
my nephew Maoz Morel, whose שבעה shiva is just wrapping up and
died defending עם ישראל Am Yisrael and מדינת ישראל, Medinat Yisrael, and
it should really be the עילוי נשמתו ilui nishmato תהי נשמתו צרורה
בצרור החיים tehi nishmato tzerurah bitzror hachayim זכר צדיק לברכה. zecher tzadik
livracha. Okay, so we begin with בשלמא bishlema and the discussion here
is when a barrel breaks or a pitcher breaks and the contents,
the honey, the wine, the oil is going to waste, the גמרא
Gemara has quoted a ברייתא braita that says that you can't make
תרומת מעשר Terumat Ma'aser on it, it's basically considered הפקר hefker at
that time when it's going to waste, and then it has to
reconcile that with different sources that seem like it's not considered הפקר.
hefker. A משנה Mishna that the honey of a barrel that's breaking
still belongs to the owner, another משנה Mishna or another ברייתא braita
that you could go ahead and transfer when your person is robbing
you, transfer it to the money that's being robbed, the sanctity of
מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, or another ברייתא braita here that's you can
do תרומת מעשר Terumat Ma'aser that is טמא, tamei, wine or oil,
the only concern on stuff that is spilling out, and the only
concern is whether it's a loss to the כהן, Kohen, and therefore
the wine which is טמא תרומה, tamei terumah, not much of a
use you can do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, the oil which can be
used for fuel, that would be a loss to the כהן Kohen
to take תרומת מעשר Terumat Ma'aser on טמא tamei oil that's in
the process of being spilled, so you shouldn't do it לכתחילה lechatchila
but בדיעבד bedieved it works. But all those cases sound like בדיעבד
bedieved it works even though the stuff is spilling out. So the
גמרא Gemara explained all of them in cases where it's not really
totally spilling out and they maybe could be saved, so either the
barrels have some type of a netting wrapped around it so it's
not breaking right away and it's spilling out and maybe there's some
possibility of saving it, the money that's being you're being robbed from,
maybe even though it's being like a highway bandit there's a possibility
of getting it back, and therefore in all those cases it's not
הפקר. hefker. That's how the גמרא Gemara deals with those issues. Okay,
now we continue with בשלמא. bishlema. בשלמא שנשברה חבית, bishlema shenishbera chavis,
so I get says the גמרא Gemara in the case where the
barrel broke, this is the case of תרומת מעשר Terumat Ma'aser that
is טמא, tamei, that you know if the wine will still be
or the oil is still usable for something even after it broke
and therefore you can בדיעבד bedieved it works or it works לכתחילה
lechatchila even by wine because it still has some value. אלא נתגלתה
למאי חזיא, ela nisgalta lemai chazya, but if it became revealed, then
you know גילוי gilluy which is of something by liquids and then
you know the גמרא Gemara thought that snakes could drink from it
and if it wasn't being watched and therefore it would become inedible
and totally useless. So if that's true, then how does that work
בדיעבד? bedieved? Shouldn't that be completely like unusable?
So למאי חזיא? lemai chazya? What good is that for? וכי תימא
חזיא לזילוף, vechi tema chazya leziluf, you can use it for air
freshener, which is what you would have used the טמא tamei wine
for anyway because again it's טמא תרומה tamei terumah so all you
can't eat it but you can use it for air freshener, so
maybe you can do that even after גילוי. gilluy. והתניא, vehatanya, but
we learn in a ברייתא, braita, מים שנתגלו, mayim shenitgalu, if you
have water that was left uncovered, הרי זה לא ישפכם ברשות הרבים,
harei zeh lo yishpechem bireshut harabbim, don't spill it in the public
domain because somebody will walk on it barefoot and maybe they'll have
a cut and it'll go into their body and the poison will
go in, that's again what the גמרא Gemara thought. ולא יגבל בהם
את הטיט velo yigabel bahem et hatit and do not use it
to mix it with like even with like plaster because again somehow
some of that liquid will go
into somebody.
ולא ירביץ בה את הבית, velo yarbitz bah et habayit, you shouldn't
use it to sprinkle on to settle the dust in a house.
All of these are such a big concern about the poison here
you have to be avoid getting in any possible type of contact
with it. ולא ישקה מהם את בהמתו, velo yashke mehem et behemto,
don't feed it to your animal because there's a concern either it'll
kill the animal or you'll eat the meat and it'll get into
your body that way. ולא בהמת חבירו, velo behemat chaveiro, not your
friend's animal. So anyway, obviously you shouldn't be able to use it
for an air freshener, you know some of that
vapor or whatever will touch your skin and so it's completely valueless
and therefore how could it become תרומת מעשר? Terumat Ma'aser? So the
גמרא Gemara says דאבר ליה במסטננא, da'avar lei bemistanena, you pass it
through a type of a sieve. Okay, a מסטננא mistanena was a
like a like you know you have it in one cup above,
sort of like you think like of a coffee filter, sometimes they
have like two vessels one on top of the other, and so
it's in the top one and there's a screen at the bottom
and it passes through, so and that will separate out. the poison
that might be in the wine. Okay, so כרבי נחמיה, k'rebi Nechemya,
this would go like רבי נחמיה. rebi Nechemya. דתניא מסננת יש בה
משום גילוי. detanya misnenes yesh bo mishum gilui. If you have this
sieve system set up, one cup on top of the other, passing
through a grate or a sieve, that still is a problem of
גילוי gilui because we basically don't feel that the sieve will get
out the poison. אמר רבי נחמיה amar rebi Nechemya but רבי נחמיה
rebi Nechemya says אימתי eimasai when is this true? בזמן שהתחתונה מגולה
bezman shehatachtona megula only if the bottom cup is exposed then obviously
the snake could drink from that poison. אבל בזמן שהתחתונה מכוסה aval
bezman shehatachtona mechusa if
the bottom one is covered, אף על פי שהעליונה מגולה af al
pi shehaelyona megula even though the top one is
exposed—and the reason I should have said that you're doing this whole
sieve thing is not it's not clearly here, it's clear that you
have this contraption set up even unrelated to the snake, and you're
doing it because you want to purify the wine, you want to
get out like all of the dregs of the wine. So anyway,
this is a this is a type of a contraption you have
set up to, you know, to filter out the wine. So if
the snake is the bottom part of that contraption is exposed under
below the filter obviously that's a problem of גילוי, gilui, but if
the top part is exposed then the filter the same way it's
filtering out the wine from, you know, grape remnants will also filter
it out from the poison. אף על פי שהתחתונה מכוסה af al
pi shehatachtona mechusa the bottom is covered, אף על פי שהעליונה מגולה
af al pi shehaelyona megula even though the top is exposed, אין
בה משום גילוי ein ba mishum gilui it's not a problem of
גילוי gilui of being exposed, of being uncovered, לפי שארס של נחש
דומה לספוג lefi she'eres shel nachash dome lisfog because the poison of
a snake is like a sponge—I'm not exactly sure what the analogy
is—וצף ועומד במקומו vetaf ve'omed bimkomo and it stays at the top
of the of the liquid and it does not go to the
bottom and therefore it'll be filtered out with the with the filter.
Okay, so therefore that's why it's the wine has not become completely
valueless and that's why the you can redeem you can make it
into תרומת מעשר. trumas ma'aser. So the גמרא gemara says one minute,
לאו איתמר עלה אמר רבי סימון אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי לא
שנו אלא שלא טרפו lav itmar ala amar rebi simon amar rebi
yehoshua ben levi lo shanu ela shelo tarfo that's only if you
did not like spill it, like you didn't actually take it and
like pour it out. אבל טרפו אסור aval tarfo assur but if
you pour it out, you know, even through a sieve it's a
problem because the sort of the, you know, the the velocity and
the water pressure when you pour it out in will actually cause
the poison to go through the sieve. So הגמרא hagemara says no,
התם נמי דאפשר דמנח מידי אפומא דחביתא. hasam nami d'efshar demaniach midi
apuma dechavisa.
So no, here too like you can do it in a—meaning it
was saying it was only okay if you had it set up
in a gradual way, you know, where it was slowly going through
the sieve, not if it was going through with a lot of
pressure. So it's assuming that the—so the answer is okay, so set
it up here it's here too when it sort of when it
was with your, you know, a pitcher of oil or of wine
also who says you have to do it with pressure? Do a
similar setup like you set up the normal מסננת misnenes system and
do it soft and, you know, and and do it gradual. הכא
נמי דאפשר דמנח מידי אפומא דחביתא hacha nami d'efshar demaniach midi apuma
dechavisa you can put something on the mouth of the barrel דשפי
ליה deshafi lei and you can sort of pour it out and
pour it out slowly and don't pour it out with a lot
of strength. Okay. Anyway, that's how the wine can still be usable.
So now of course the question is if it's if that's what
you can do, then why shouldn't you do it לכתחילה lechatchila if
it's oil and why, you know, what's the whole issue to begin
with? And the answer basically is you can do it but it's
a pain in the neck, so, you know, to give that to
the כהן kohen where the כהן kohen then has to be very
careful to not, you know, to pass it through the sieve and
the whole type of a thing, right, that's why it's a problem
by the oil but again by the wine we're not so bothered.
Okay,
because that's not of a high use. So now the גמרא gemara
says like this, ורבי נחמיה מי תרמינא verebi nechemya mi tarmina
according to רבי נחמיה—because rebi nechemya רבי נחמיה rebi nechemya just gave
this answer about, you know, רבי נחמיה rebi nechemya was the one
who was used in terms of this issue of the sieve and
the and the problem of גילוי gilui of the exposed wine—how can
we say that that ברייתא braisa is going like רבי נחמיה? rebi
nechemya? That ברייתא braisa doesn't fit in with another teaching of רבי
נחמיה. rebi nechemya. We had to invoke רבי נחמיה rebi nechemya to
explain how the wine is still usable, but it doesn't work with
another teaching. Why, what does רבי נחמיה rebi nechemya teach? דתניא detanya
we learn in a ברייתא, braisa, תורמין מן הטמא על הטמא tormin
min hatame al hatame you can take תרומה טמאה truma tame on
grain that's טמא, tame, מן הטהור על הטהור min hatahor al hatahor
and תרומה טהורה truma tehora on טהור, tahor, מן הטהור על הטמא
min hatahor al hatame you can take תרומה טהורה truma tehora on
grain that's טמא, tame, אבל לא מן הטמא על הטהור aval lo
min hatame al hatahor but you can't take from טמא tame grain
on טהור tahor grain obviously because, you know, the כהן kohen is
losing out, you're giving him something of lesser value than the grain
itself. רבי נחמיה אומר אף מן הטמא על הטמא לא התירו לתרום
אלא בשל דמאי rebi nechemya omer af min hatame al hatame lo
hitiru litrom ela beshel demai even from טמא tame to טמא tame
you're not allowed to do except in the case of דמאי demai
otherwise you always have to try to give the כהן kohen תרומה
טהורה truma tehora even if your grain is טמא. tame. but it's
only allowed by דמאי *demai*, which is grain bought from an עם
הארץ *am haaretz*, which has questionable might be תרומות *trumas* and מעשרות
*maasros* were already taken from it. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, so if רבי Rebbi, נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemya*, if this idea
of the wine, it's considered to still have value because it's going
like רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemya* about the sieve, then how come the
whole point is you're taking this טמא *tamei* wine that's spilling and
you're and you're separating it as תרומה *trumah* on the remainder of
the טמא *tamei* grain that you have in your house? But that
doesn't work for רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemya*. Now of course they're completely
different positions, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, so you could
just say it's different opinion, you hold like רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemya*
in one case, not the other, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gives
a different answer. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, הכא נמי בשל
דמאי *hacha nami beshel demai*, if you want all this to go
like רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemya*, say that we're talking about דמאי *demai*.
And רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemya* agrees you can do טמא *tamei* on
טמא *tamei* for דמאי *demai*. אמר מר ובשמן לא יעשה כן מפני
הפסד כהן *Amar mar uvshemen lo yaaseh kein mipnei hefsed kohein*. Okay,
so we let you do this by the wine, even though it's
now, you know, dripping out or it's going to be you're going
to have to pass it through a sieve or whatever, we let
you do because it's not a big, that's why we let you
do because it's not going to be a significant loss. Wine, טמא
תרומה *tamei trumah* wine, is very, has very little use, but for
oil we don't let you do it because that would be a
significant loss to a כהן *kohein*, because it could be used for
fuel. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ובשמן לא יעשה כן מפני
הפסד כהן *uvshemen lo yaaseh kein mipnei hefsed kohein*, you can't do
because it'll the loss to the כהן *kohein*. מאי שנא שמן *Mai
shna shemen*? Why is oil a problem, problematic? דחזי להדלקה *Dechazi l'hadlaka*,
because the כהן *kohein* can use it, even though it's
טמא *tamei*, for illumination. He can use it for his oil lamps.
יין נמי חזי לזילוף *Yayin nami chazi l'ziluf*, wine can be used
for air freshener, for sprinkling, and you can use טמא *tamei* wine
for that, as long as it doesn't have poison. וכי תימא זילוף
לאו מלתא היא *V'chi teima ziluf lav milta hee*. Oh, you say,
okay, but you know what? That's very, very little value, air freshener,
it's a tiny, tiny benefit. אבל הא *Aval ha*, is that really
true? והאמר שמואל משום רבי חייא שוסין מלוג בסלע מזלפין מלוג בשתים
*V'ha'amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Chiyya shosin milog besela mazalfin milog beshtayim*. You
should be prepared to buy a לוג *log* of wine for drinking
purposes for one סלע *sela*, but if you're buying them for sprinkling
purposes and air freshener purposes, then you should get higher quality and
you should be prepared to pay two סלעים *slaim*. So it is
actually, I mean, maybe you only lose a little at a time,
but it actually is a serious use and has some real value.
So isn't that also an issue of הפסד כהן *hefsed kohein* if
even in the case of the wine that's going to waste? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הכא במאי עסקינן בחדש *hacha bemai askinan
bechadash*, it's new wine and new wine doesn't do such a good
job, it's not so aromatic of air freshening, so it's worth very
little. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והא חזי לישן *v'ha chazi
l'yashon*, okay, but wait a minute, new wine can become old, so
it will have value and it is, כהן *kohein* is losing something
out there of something of real value. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, no, אתי בה לידי תקלה takala. *ati bah lidei takalah*, we
wouldn't let the כהן *kohein* keep it around and let it get
old. We would tell the כהן *kohein* he has to use it
right away if you gave him new wine that was טמא *tamei*,
because if he kept it around, eventually he might, for a long
time, I mean, how much wine do you use at any time
to just sprinkle in the air, keeps it around for a few
years, he'll forget that it's טמא *tamei* and he might come to
drink from it. So we would demand that he use it right
away and therefore that type of a wine has very little market
value, and therefore we allow you to do it and we're not
worried about the loss to the כהן *kohein*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, שמן נמי אתי לידי תקלה takala. *shemen nami ati lidei
takalah*, one minute, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but you don't use
the oil right away, takes you time to use the oil. So
why aren't we afraid that you'll come to eat from it? גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, no, דמנח
בכלי מאוס *demanach bichli maus*, you put it in a disgusting vessel.
So you put it in something that, because who cares, you're using
it for fuel, so you put it in something that you would
never want to eat from after that, and it's very obvious, so
there's no concern you might come to eat from it. יין נמי
מנח ליה בכלי מאוס *Yayin nami manach lei bichli maus*, and says,
so why not do the same with the wine you're using for
an air freshener, and therefore you should be allowed to leave it
around until it gets old? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* gives the
obvious answer, השתא לזילוף קבעי ליה בכלי מאוס קמנח ליה *hashta l'ziluf
kabaei lei bichli maus kamanach lei*? You want to use it for
an air freshener because it's aromatic, you're not going to put it
in some disgusting vessel. So because you're want to going to keep
it fresh and clean and aromatic, then you might come to use
the wine. So the wine we would only allow you to use
right away, but the oil you could take your time with because
there's, because you can make sure you don't come to eat from
it. Now the גמרא *Gemara* says, last line of קט"ו עמוד ב'
*Kuf Tes Vav Amud Beis*, הא דרב הונא גופא תנאי היא *Ha
d'Rav Huna gufa tanaei hee*. The issue about a concern of coming
to accidentally use from it, like with טמא תרומה *tamei trumah*, leaving
it around, is a debate of תנאים *tannaim*. דתניא *Detanya*, we turn
the ברייתא Beraita, *braisa*, חבית של יין של תרומה שנטמאת *Chavis shel
yayin shel trumah shenitmeis*, you have a barrel of wine of תרומה
*trumah* that became טמא *tamei*. בית שמאי Beit Shammai אומרים *Beis Shammai
omrim*, top of קט"ז עמוד א' *Kuf Tes Zayin Amud Aleph*, בית
שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* says, תשפך הכל *tishafeich hakol*, you have
to spill it, we're afraid you'll come to eat from it. ובית
הלל אומרים תעשה זילוף *u'Beis Hillel omrim taaseh ziluf*, you can use
it for air freshener. Okay,
exactly this issue, so בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* allows you
to use it for air freshener, presumably if you start using it.
right away, given our earlier discussion. You don't hold on to it
for a few years and then use it. Okay, but we don't
know, בית הלל Beit Hillel didn't even say that. So בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai, disagree, בית הלל Beit Hillel.
at least in, at least in some cases, and the standard cases,
not concerned for תקלה. takala אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Amar Rabbi
Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose said רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose,
אני אכריע, ani achriya, I will come, I will sort of come
to a compromise position, or I will weigh in favor here and
come to a decision about this, about this debate. בבית תעשה זילוף
בשדה תשפכהו הכל. Bevait taaseh ziluf besadeh tishpocheihu hakol.
If the wine is in the house, then you can use it
for air freshener, you'll start using it right away and we're not
afraid that you'll come to eat from it, you'll remember that it's
there for air freshener. But if it's out in the field, nobody
needs air freshener out in the field, then we demand that you
spill it because by the time as you're שלעפינג schlepping it to
the house, you might forget and have some of it on the
way by the time you get around to bringing it to the
house and on the way. Okay, so איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some
say, בישן תעשה זילוף בחדש תשפכהו הכל. Beyashan taaseh ziluf bechadash tishpocheihu
hakol. He did the split in a different way based on the
distinction that we just did. If it's old wine, then you can
use it, but if it's new wine, you can't, because we're afraid
maybe that you won't use it at all and if
you go ahead and use it,
the new one, if it's new, therefore,
it doesn't work so well, it has very little value, a tiny
value as an air freshener, so we don't let you, that we
demand that you spill it because we're afraid you'll leave it around
until it gets old, and at that stage, you will, by the
time it gets old, you will accidentally come to benefit from it,
to eat it, so that's a concern of תקלה. takala. But if
it's old and you start using it right away, we're not concerned.
Okay, בישן תעשה זילוף בחדש תשפכהו הכל. Beyashan taaseh ziluf bechadash tishpocheihu
hakol. Like sort of the distinction we made before. Okay, and the
גמרא says, אמרו לו, amru lo, so they said back to him,
I'm sorry, let's cross the line. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
back to him, אין הכרעה שלישית מכרעת. ein hachra'a shelishit machra'at. So
בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai said back to
him, you're a third opinion, you don't get to decide between us.
Now, what does this mean? It sounds like a good middle position,
it takes into concerns the issue about will it come to a
תקלה takala, or not a תקלה. takala, It says it depends on
certain cases, some cases it's more likely to come to a תקלה,
we'll rule like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai. other cases less likely to
come to a תקלה, we'll rule like בית הלל. Beit Hillel, Isn't
that a good compromise position? So רש״י Rashi says the way you
determine the logic, the way something has a weight as like a
third position that allows us to sort of come to a decision
between the two combating ones by coming to some middle position is
only when the first two positions recognized the logic of the distinction
even if they didn't weigh in favor of it. Meaning, if
בית שמאי Beit Shammai had said you have to spill it out
whether it's old or new, you have to spill it out whether
it's in the field or in the home, and בית הלל Beit
Hillel said you can use it whether it's old or new, you
can use it whether it's in the field or the home, that
means that they sort of recognize these distinctions but they still said
we're going to be מחמיר machmir or מקיל meykil in all cases.
And then comes along רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose
and he says some cases I'll פסקן pasken like בית הלל, Beit
Hillel some cases I'll פסקן pasken like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. In
that type of a case, he is a middle position and therefore
we would go in favor of it. Whereas here, בית הלל and
בית שמאי just said their stuff categorically. They're not willing to consider
other factors at all. One is just generally I am not concerned
with it, the other says generally I am concerned. So to say,
well it depends on context, is really a completely new approach. It's
not an approach that partly recognizes בית הלל and partly recognizes בית
שמאי. Okay, so that's how רש״י Rashi explains that idea of דעת
שלישית, da'at shelishit, הכרעה שלישית. hachra'a shelishit. Okay,
now we continue. אם אמר לו אציל את שלך, Im amar lo
atzil et shelcha, finally we're back to the משנה. Mishnah. If he
stipulates and says, fine I'll save yours as if you're willing to
pay me for mine, then that is a binding agreement and then
he has to pay for the loss.
אמאי? Amai? This is in the case of spilling out my wine
to save your honey. Why is that true?
ונימא ליה משטה אני בך? Uneima leh meshahta ani bach? Why can't
he tell you, why can't the guy who said fine I'll pay
you for your wine, then when the guy does it, why can't
he say, yeah I was just kidding, like I'm not going to
pay you for your wine, I'm only going to pay you for
your service. Now, the obvious answer would be because you made the
agreement and on the basis of the agreement I was willing to
actually spill out my wine. So, but let's take a look. The
גמרא is asking the question because there's another case where you are
able to say it. So it's really asking it just to make
the distinction. Let's take a look. מי לא תניא, Mi lo tanya,
do we not teach in a ברייתא, Baraita היה שבוי בורח מבית
האסורים, Haya shavui boreach mibeit ha'asurim, somebody was running away from jail
and presumably it's like the non-Jewish
jail so he's a good guy, he's not a felon that you
want to turn back in, והייתה מעבורת
לפניו, Vehayta maaboret lefanav, and there was a boat used for crossing
across a river that was right there on his side of the
river. אמר לו טול דינר והעבירני, Amar lo tol dinar vehaavireni, and
he says, here, take a thousand dollars and cross me. And help
me, you know, get me across to the other side, אין לו
אלא שכרו ein lo ela sekharo and then he does it. So
the הלכה halakha is because this person running away from the בית
האסורים beit ha'asurim is a תלמיד חכם talmid chakham or whatever, eventually
they go to a בית דין beit din and the הלכה halakha
is he only has to pay him for the normal cost of
passing of bringing somebody to the other side of the river. עלמא
אמר ליה משוטה אני בך alma amar lei meshaden bak so you
see he can say, "Ah, I was just kidding, you know, I'll
give you a million dollars if you help me." And at the
end of the day, though, he just performed for him a normal
service, and therefore how is that any different, you know, than our
case? So why in our case also don't you just pay him
for the normal service, why do you have to pay him the
higher amount that was agreed? Now the difference is obvious, so let's
take a look. הכא נמי לימא ליה משוטה אני בך hacha nami
leima lei meshaden bak so why here can't you just say, "Yeah,
I was promising you a lot of money, but I was just
exaggerating"? So the גמרא says הלא דמיא אלא לסיפא. halo damya ela
leseifa. No, no, no, our case in the משנה Mishnah is not
similar to the first case of paying the guy to cross you
over, the ferryman, it's similar to the second case. What's the second
case? ואם אמר לו טול דינר זה בשכרך והעבירני נותן לו שכרו
משלו. ve'im amar lo tol dinars zeh besakharkha veha'avirani noten lo skharo
mishelo. If you say not just I'll give you a thousand dollars,
I will pay you a thousand dollars for your fee, then you
do have to pay him. What's the difference? מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? mai shna reisha mai shna seifa? Okay, explain to me
the logic of the difference. So the גמרא says אמר רבי בר
חמא amar Rabbi Bar Chama בציידא דשלו דגים מני ים. betzaida deshilo
dagim mini yam. Let's say the guy was actually so you could
have said somehow the word בשכרך besakharkha is the difference, the circumstances
are the same, you know, in terms of what this ferryman was
doing, but when you say I'll give you a thousand dollars it's
like, you know, that's just like as a reward and that doesn't
really obligate. When you say I will pay it to you as
your fee, a fee for services, you know, then that's the price
that you stipulated on for the services. So that is what the
ברייתא sounds like, the difference is as whether it's a fee or
a reward. But the גמרא actually wants to make it more of
a
substantive difference in terms of what the actual person was doing, so
let's see what the גמרא says. And the גמרא says בציידא דשלו
דגים מני ים betzaida deshilo dagim mini yam
that the ferryman was actually, you know, he wasn't just a ferryman
or wasn't even a ferryman, he was
really a fisherman and he was there and he was catching fish.
ואמר ליה אפסדתני כוורי בזוזא v'amar lei afsadeitani kavari bezzuza
and he says will say to you, you made me lose my
fish with the, you know, the I took the זוז zuz and
I was willing to sacrifice, you know, the fish I was going
to catch. So basically it turns this distinction exactly into our משנה.
Mishnah. And the point is is that if the guy is actually
incurring a loss then and you agree to pay for that loss
for the opportunity cost, for the actual loss, I will pay you
for your expenses, you know, then that is part of the agreement
and then you are obligated to pay. If however he's not incurring
a loss, even if you promised to give him more money, you
are not obligated. So that's actually quite a big חידוש, chiddush, cause
you could have understood that if you promise a reward you might
not be obligated, but if you're promising an actual higher fee, you
know, you would be, but the גמרא is here saying no, like
people don't have to pay more than the service was worth, but
you know if the person was but if there was a loss
and it was agreed upon then that obligates. And that's what it
does with the case of the guy running out of the jail.
You also I think wonder about what if the person is exposing
himself to risk, right, not like he's a fisherman and he's losing
the income of fishing but like he might get caught by, you
know, the prison guards or by the government or so on. One
would imagine that there also you could actually ask for agree upon
a higher price. So what this means is is that you know
you can't have like quote unquote highway robbery, you know, you can't
have exploitative pricing and taking advantage of somebody's bad situation, but if
you are actually suffering a loss and I would add exposing yourself
to risk, then you could ask for agree upon a price and
that would obligate. Okay. שטף נהר חמורו וחמור חברו שלו יפה ומנה
וכו׳. sataf nahar chamoro vechamor chavero shelo yafe umane et cetera. Now
we do a similar case except instead of honey and wine it's
two donkeys, one of them is, you know, is worth 200, one
100, you abandon yours and you go save the other one. וצריכא
utrichah
the גמרא says you need to tell me both cases. דאי אשמעינן
קמייתא de'i ashmi'inan kamaitha if it just told me the case of
the wine and honey, התם הוא דכי פריש יהיב ליה דמי כולי,
hatam hu dechi pirish yahiv lei dmei kulei, that's when you stipulate
to be reimbursed for the wine he has to pay it. משום
דבידיה קא מפסיד ליה mishum deveyada kapasidei because I actually actively spilled
out my wine because you told me you would reimburse. אבל הכא
דממילא aval hacha demimeila
but here where I'm losing my donkey and it's just letting it
happen passively, נימא אין לו אלא שכרו, neima ein lo ela skharo,
you might say even though you stipulated you didn't actually, you know,
expend or or waste something on my say so, you just didn't
actively go ahead and save your donkey, maybe I don't have I'm
not obligated to reimburse even if I promised you that was not
a real... direct expense. So teaches you, yes, since that is loss
that I incurred, even in a passive way, and you agreed to
reimburse me, you have to pay. ואשמעינן סיפא, v'ashmeinan seifa, and if
it had just told me the case about the donkey, הכא הוא
דבסתמא אין לו אלא שכרו, hacha hu de-bistama ein lo ela secharo,
that's when you didn't stipulate, that's when you need to stipulate. If
you didn't stipulate, you wouldn't be able to charge for it, משום
דממילא קאזיל, mishum de-mimailei ka-azil, the loss only happens passively. אבל התם
דבידים, aval hatam d'b'yadayim, but in the wine and the honey, I
might have thought that since I'm actively spilling my wine, אימא אפילו
בסתמא יהיב ליה דמי כוליה, eima afilu bistama yahiv lei d'mei kulei,
even if you did not agree to pay for the loss, you
have to because that was a direct expense incurred through saving your
honey, which makes a lot of sense, I think some of us
might feel that that should be the case. Anyway, so אימא אפילו
בסתמא יהיב ליה דמי כוליה, eima afilu bistama yahiv lei d'mei kulei,
צריכא, tzricha, so you need both cases, that whether it's passive or
active, if you don't make a stipulation, you don't pay for the
expense, and if you do make a stipulation, you do. Fine. בעי
מיניה רב כהנא מרב, ba'ei minei Rav Kahana mi-Rav, five lines from
the wide lines. בעי מיניה רב כהנא מרב, ba'ei minei Rav Kahana
mi-Rav, Rav Kahana asked Rav: ירד להציל ועלה שלו מאליו מהו? yarad
l'hatzil v'ala shelo me'elav mahu? Let's say you went to save the
guy's donkey, and you saved the guy's donkey, and then your donkey
actually managed to survive. So does he have to pay you what
he stipulated? אמר ליה משמיא רחימו עליה, amar lei mishmaya rachimu alei,
that yes, you had, you know, from heaven they had compassion on
you, and basically you agreed, the guy agreed, since you were going
ahead and risking the loss and you know he agreed to pay,
he didn't say "if your donkey dies," you said "I will save
yours if you give me, but I am charging you the price
of my donkey plus whatever other charges," and he agreed to it.
So because of the risk and because you were incurring that risk,
or assumed loss, that agreed-upon price was binding, and even though in
the end you didn't suffer the risk, okay, you come out ahead.
Okay. כי הא דרב ספרא, ki ha d'Rav Safra, like the case
of Rav Safra. הוה קאזיל בשיירתא, hava ka-azil b'shayarta, he was going
on a caravan. לויינהו ההוא ארי, livinehu hahu ari,
and a lion was accompanying them, excuse me, לויינהו ההוא ארי, livinehu
hahu ari, and a lion was accompanying them, okay, they had a
trained lion there to guard the camp. כל ליליא כד שדי ליה
חמרא חד מנייהו. kol lelya kad shadi lei chamra chad mineihu.
Every day they would sort of
send the lion a donkey for dinner,
and they would take turns, you know, each one would give a
donkey each night. ואכיל ליה, v'achil lei, and the lion would eat
it. כי מטא זמניה דרב ספרא, ki mata zimnei d'Rav Safra, when
Rav Safra's turn came, שדא ליה חמרא, shada lei chamra, they sent
it a donkey, ולא אכליה, v'lo achlei, it didn't eat it. קדים
רב ספרא וזכה ביה, kadim Rav Safra v'zacha bei, so Rav Safra
went and he took possession of it. He said, okay, like, that
was my donkey, and I did my turn, I, you know, gave
it. I don't have to now give my donkey the next night.
I gave it this night. And then he took possession, and we'll
see why he had to take possession, why didn't he just say
it was still his donkey. But the basic point though being that
he did what he was supposed to do, and it wasn't agreed
that he would have to lose a donkey, just that he had
to give it for dinner. And therefore he got, he lucked out.
אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, amar lei Rav Acha mi-Difti l'Ravina,
so now Rav Acha mi-Difti said to Ravina, למה לי למזכא ביה?
lama li l'mizka bei? Why did he have to actually re-possess it?
נהי דכי אפקריה אדעתא דאריה אפקריה אדעתא דכולי עלמא לא אפקריה. nehi
de-ki afkrei ada'ata d'arya afkrei ada'ata d'kulei alma lo afkrei.
It's true he basically like was מפקיר mafkir it, meaning he sort
of gave up any ownership. He assumed that the lion was going
to eat it. But he wasn't really saying "this donkey is now
ownerless, anybody can come and take it." He was doing it on
the assumption the lion would eat it. But if the lion for
whatever reason chose to not eat it, and sort of Tosafot explains
it's not like it was assumed that it was definitely going to
happen, okay, it was assumed, you know, there was always a possibility
it might not eat it. So he was not willing, he wasn't
giving up ownership even if the lion didn't eat it. אמר ליה,
amar lei, Rav Safra to Rav Acha, דמילתא הוא דעביד. d'milta hu
d'avid. Yeah, it's true, he really still owned it, but you know,
he didn't want other people to say "hey, that's not fair, you
know, and we should be able to take possession of it, let's
all split the donkey or something." So therefore he did it so
that there should not be any question about it. But technically speaking,
he never really gave up his ownership over it and he also
did not have to provide the donkey the next night because he
did his obligation. So here too would be the same. Rashi sort
of, you know, because he basically they stipulated, that's what has to
be paid, and if at the end the thing didn't get washed
away,
then still that's the agreement we paid from it and I just
got lucky, you know, and I just got lucky the same way
Rav Safra got lucky. Rashi says in the case of the donkey
that you would have to re-take possession of the donkey, but that's
not so clear. It could have been that, you know, like the
Rav Safra case, that he wasn't actually giving up his ownership of
the donkey and he automatically owns it. he never lost owning it
in the case where his donkey survives when you chased after the
other donkey. However, it does seem that the scenario is one where
that it would be expected that under normal circumstances his donkey would
be totally lost, and that is a principle the גמרא calls אבודה
ממנו ומכל אדם, avudah mimenu umikol adam, so that actually would have
rendered the donkey הפקר, hefker, which is how רש"י Rashi understands it.
So he would get his pay for saving the other person's donkey,
and then his donkey would be free for the taking, and if
he sees it then he would get that as well. Okay, so
now we continue here and we pick up with בעי מיניה, bei
minei, two lines again from the bottom, בעי מיניה רב מרבי. bei
minei Rav merebbi. So רב Rav asked רבי, ירד להציל ולא הציל
מהו. yarad lehatzil velo hitzil mahu. Let's say he went to save
the donkey, the $200 donkey, and he didn't succeed in saving it.
Does he still get not only his fee for services, but also
the $100 for his lost donkey? Was he stipulating that for his
attempt to save it, or was he stipulating that that's what he
would have be paid if he actually did save it? אמר לו,
amar lo, so he said back, וזו שאלה? vezo she'eilah? Is that
a question? אין לו אלא שכרו. ein lo ela secharo. You'll only
get your fee for the effort, you'll get paid. But the idea
that you had agreed and stipulated on a higher price, that was
on the assumption that you actually, the higher price meaning to pay
you back for your losses of your $100 donkey, that actually was
based on the assumption that you would succeed in getting his $200
donkey. It wasn't to give it your best try; it was to
actually retrieve the donkey.
Okay. אתיבי, eitivei, challenge this. השוכר את הפועל, hasocher et hapoel, now
turning the page קטז עמוד ב, kuf tet vav amud bet, somebody
who hires a worker להביא לו כרוב ודורמסקין lehavi lo keruv vedurmaskin
to bring him cabbage and plums לחולה lecholeh for a sick person.
For some reason this was specifically something that was needed for this
sick person, and presumably you had to pay him an, you agreed
on an extra fee because this was hard to get. והלך ומצאו
שמת vehalach umatza'o shemet and then he went and he brought back
the cabbage and plums, but when he came back the sick person
was already dead או שהבריא o shehivri or he got better. One
way or the other, he didn't need the cabbage or the plums.
So נותן לו שכרו משלם. noten lo secharo mishalem. You have to
give him the full payment, meaning even if even though you agreed
to pay him more because it was an extra effort to find
these specific ingredients that were needed for the חולה, choleh, and even
though now it's they're no longer needed, you still have to pay
him the full stipulated-upon price. Now the obvious difference is clear. It's
true that in both of those
cases your efforts weren't needed, but in one case you did what
you were, you succeeded and in one case you didn't, which is
exactly what the גמרא says. אמר לו מי דמי, amar lo mi
dami, he said back, how can you compare them? התם עבד שליחותיה
הכא לא עבד שליחותיה. hatam avad shelichuteih hacha lo avad shelichuteih.
In that case, you brought back the cabbage and the plums. It
just wasn't needed anymore, but you did exactly what you said, so
you get the price agreed upon. In our case, you did not
do what you had agreed upon. You said you were actually going
to retrieve the donkey. If you had said "I will make my
best effort to get it and you'll agree to pay me for
my lost donkey," then fine. But if you didn't say that, and
you said "I'll run after yours and you give me mine," then
the presumption is is that that means that you are being paid
that extra for the loss of your donkey, not just for your
efforts but actually for your success. Okay. Now we continue with issues
relating to sort of stipulations. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. שיירא שהייתה מהלכת
במדבר ועמד עליה גייס לטורפה. shayara shehayetah mahalechet bamidbar ve'amad aleha gayis
letorfah.
A caravan that was going in the wilderness and troops came in
order to seize it, to attack it, and they had to pay
a ransom in order to get out without being killed. מחשבין לפי
ממון ואין מחשבין לפי נפשות. mechashevin lefi mamon ve'ein mechashevin lefi nefashot.
So let's say the ransom was $1,000 and there are two people
there and one person's net worth or maybe the money carrying with
him, it's not exactly clear, was nine times the other. So that
person who's had a higher net worth or was carrying nine times
as much money would pay $900 and the other person would pay
$100. Which makes sense
because they are being attacked for their money. So therefore when they
have to be paid off, and presumably if they had been robbed
they would have been robbed proportional to the amount of money they
were carrying, so then when they are paying off it is divided
proportionally based on their wealth. Again, not exactly clear if it's based
on the money they have with them or their net worth. ואם
שכרו תייר ההולך לפניהם, ve'im sacharu tayar haholech lifneihem,
now let's say they hired a tour guide or a scout rather
to go before them and to scout out the way to make
sure that they would survive the path through the desert and also
not get attacked. So in that case מחשבין אף לפי נפשות. mechashevin
af lefi nefashot.
They also compute it based on the souls and not just based
on the wealth, because that scout is both protecting them from attack
from
banditry and highwaymen and also protecting them from dying in the desert.
So therefore, it's not exactly tell you how you exactly figure it
out, but let's say they agree to pay him $100, and let's
use a... case about nine, nine, one person has nine times as
much wealth than the other. So maybe what you do is you
take the first fifty dollars and they each pay twenty-five, and then
you take the next fifty dollars and that you divide and one
person pays whatever, nine, 90% of that and the other person pays
10% of that. Okay, so that's how you do it because in
that case the person is
doing an equal service to them in terms of protecting their lives,
but an unequal service to them in terms of protecting their money.
ולא ישנו ממנהג החמרים v'lo yeshano miminhag hachamarim and all of that
is if you didn't stipulate explicitly and if there is no preset
practice amongst the donkey drivers, amongst the people that
or the scouts, because if there is a normal way in which
it's divided, the bill is divided and you don't stipulate otherwise, then
you would go by the normal practice. Similarly, רשאים החמרים להתנות שכל
מי שיאבד לו חמור יעמיד לו חמור אחר. rashaim hachamarim l'hatnot shekol
mi sheyovad lo chamor yaamid lo chamor acher.
Donkey drivers can stipulate, sort of like a union or a guild,
that if anybody loses their donkey in the normal course of business,
that the other donkey drivers will give him another donkey, sort of
like an insurance. And we'll see in a minute and it might
also be to their benefit as well. And once they make that
stipulation, then they can force one another to live by it. Now,
יעמיד לו חמור אחר. yaamid lo chamor acher. בחוסיא אין מעמידין לו,
שלא בחוסיא מעמידין לו. b'chusia ein maamidim lo, shelo b'chusia maamidim lo.
בחוסיא b'chusia is a word that means with negligence. If there's even
if they agreed to that, if the one person lost their donkey
due to negligence, then they do not have to replace it. But
if it was not due to negligence, then that would be their
stipulation, they would have to replace it. ואם אמר תנו לי ואני
אשמור. v'im amar tnu li v'ani eshmor. Now, let's say the guy
who lost his donkey said, you know what? My donkey was worth
a hundred dollars. Don't buy me another donkey. Just give me a
hundred dollars, that'll be fine. And maybe then I'll continue to watch
your donkeys. What it seems here now is that part of the
reason that they would replace his donkey is that they would take
turns watching the donkeys. And if you had your donkey amongst the
group, you had skin in the game, then you would be extra
careful, make an extra effort to do a good job in terms
of watching them. So it was partly self-interest that they would replace
his donkey so that when it became his turn to watch, he
would also have a self-interest in doing a good job. So if
he says, just give me my money and I promise I'll watch
it just as good, you don't do that. The deal was that
we replace your donkey. פשיטא pshita says the גמרא, obvious. לא צריכה
דאית ליה חמרא אחרינא. lo tzricha d'it lei chamra achrina. We could
be talking about that he has another donkey and he lost one
of them. מהו דתימא קא מנטר להו. mahu d'teima ka mantar lehu.
So I might think, look, he's watching the group of donkeys and
he does have skin in the game because one of the donkeys
is his. So maybe he can just pocket the other hundred dollars
and he doesn't have to buy another donkey with it. קא משמע
לן שינוי נטירותא דחד מנטירותא דבי תרי. ka mashma lan shinui netiruta
d'chad minetiruta d'bei terei. It's different when you're watching one of your
donkeys and when you're watching two. The more skin you have in
the game, the better you will watch it. So it is not
pay somebody for their lost donkey, it is actually replacing their donkey.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Our Rabbis taught. ספינה שהיתה מהלכת בים. sfina
shehaita mehalechet bayam. עמד עליה נחשול לטובעה. amad aleha nachshol l'tovah. So
a boat was going in the sea and a big wave came
in order and was going
to drown it, what's the better word, to capsize it.
והקילו ממשאה. v'hikilu mimasah. Sort of like a יונה Yona story, and
they threw off some of the load in order that it could
survive these heavy sea conditions. מחשבין לפי משא ואין מחשבין לפי ממון.
mechashvin lefi masa v'ein mechashvin lefi mamon. So what you do is
you decide you divide how much of the load to throw off
based on the load that people is bringing on, not based on
the value. So if one person is bringing on boxes of sand
and he has a thousand pounds, and another person is bringing
on boxes of let's say
plums that might be worth a lot more, but they weigh a
lot less, so you don't say let's figure out how much money
this guy's load is worth and how much money that guy is
and we'll throw off a bigger proportion to the guy who has
more valuable load. No, you say how much weight does this guy
have and how much weight does that guy have? This guy has
ten times as much weight, so we tend to throw off ten
times as much of his load than we throw off of the
next guy's load. Okay, all that makes a lot of sense because
that's what's sort of necessitating things to be thrown off.
ולא
ישנו ממנהג הספנים. v'lo yeshano miminhag hasapanim. But ultimately if there's already
a practice amongst seafarers and amongst people that lead boats and captains,
then you go by whatever the norm of the practice is. ורשאים
הספנים להתנות שכל מי שתאבד לו ספינה יעמיד לו ספינה אחרת. v'rashaim
hasapanim l'hatnot shekol mi shetoavad lo sfina yaamid lo sfina acheret. Similar
to the donkeys, these also the captains or whatever the seafarers can
agree that if anybody's boat is sunk, that they would replace the
boat, presumably not the wares, but replace the boat.
אבדה לו בחוסיא אין מעמידין. avda lo b'chusia ein maamidin. שלא בחוסיא
מעמידין לו. shelo b'chusia maamidin lo. ואי פירש למקום שאין ספינות הולכות
ve'i peirash limakom she'ein sfinos holchos אין מעמידין ein ma'amidin but if
the guy took also his boat to a place he took it
more distant than the boats normally go, that would be considered negligent
and they would not have to replace it. Okay, we'll end with
this here and we'll pick up tomorrow.